<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Notes and stuff</title>
		<description></description>
		<link>http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook</link>
		<atom:link href="http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Civil society in Turkey</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Reference: article from &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;hann_civil_1996&quot;&gt;(Hann and Dunn 1996)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jenny B. White’s argument is that civic cultures exist in Turkey on a community level that precedes and upon which social movements build their networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also compare these “informal” community ties and political space to the more regulated organizations, arguing that the former are usually left behind in academic literature and therefore seriously understudied and under-represented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two main problematic points come out by overcoming this misrepresentation, firstly we can see that civil society might be possible in Islamic countries and, as a cosequence for this, that a democratizing discourse is possible in Islam based cultures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem about the underrepresentation of these supposedly informal communities is that they can be mistakenly confounded with kinship-based relationship thus leaving them outside of the definition of &lt;em&gt;civil society&lt;/em&gt; as forms of exclusion instead of inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her fieldwork the Author found that among working class and urban poors develop forms of hybrid associations, that aren’t based on kinship (or common ancestors) nor by formal membership contracts (thus not easily identifiable on a bureaucratic basis). In her argument she sustains that these associations are born to address very specific community based problems, thus they can be short lived, nonetheless they represent forms of self-organization like grassroots movements as forms of reaction to perceived(?) problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand they might be very different than “formal” organizations like human rights groups, both in the members’ composition (which is usually middle-class and well educated) in their scopes (community based tend to address very practical issues with a narrower scope of action, like water shortage in the neighbourhood) but also in their reflexivity (this is actually a guess from me)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exclusion of popular, grassroots informal movements from the conceptualizatoin of civil society becomes more problematic in contexts where specific roles exclude categories of people from the public sphere, as for example in Turkey where the gendered role of women (in particular in poor neighbourhoods or in rural areas )puts serious limits to their agency as political activists or social civil actors. In this case for example informal activism contributes to create a parallel political space where women’s participation is not seen with disproval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her research in Umraniye she found that women, although being limited by their gendered role and sometimes also excluded from the workforce for that, participate in neighbourhood life through an extended net of reciprocal indebtedness and mutual help. There isn’t any expectation for a personal return besides the knowledge that the community will come to your help in case of need: the expectation of a direct reciprocity is here moved to an expectation of reciprocity (solidarity) from the community rather than from an individual who has a “social debt” with you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important thing is to keep relstions open ended, rther than closing them through direct reciprocation. This creates a broad communal web of mutual indebtedness, which provides long erm security. […] The question then […] should not be whether civil society and democracy are compatible with Islam, but rather to what extent particular state ideologies (of which Islam is but one of many) nourish civic culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-hann_civil_1996&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hann, C. M, and Elizabeth Dunn. 1996. &lt;em&gt;Civil Society: Challenging Western Models&lt;/em&gt;. London; New York: Routledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/11/jenny_b_white</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/11/jenny_b_white</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Role of Labour Unions in Turkey’s Passive Revolution</title>
				<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The significant role of social movements for the democratization discourse is mainly due to their ability to play the role of watchdog regarding government’s activities. In particular for its ability to reveal governance practices not compatible to the rule of law and to help manage and prevent dissent. The degree of organizational solidarity between the actors of the civil sphere is a main factor in predicting their relative strength and therefore its freedom of acting and confronting the state in the political sphere. The pivotal role of labour unions in coordinating and improving the interrelations between social movements can be ascribed to their organizational peculiarities and access to resources. As mass movements of workers, unions have the possibility to influence directly the productive sector, therefore they have the capability to exercise leverage on the government and entrepreneurs by means like strikes and collective bargaining. The possibility to organize collective protests and public manifestations of dissent represent forms of resistance against state coercion. Moreover the role in conveying labour force to the formal sector of economy and diverting dissent in legal and peaceful protests is a prerogative of well established unions that can boost the overall performance of a country. Preventing (or at least limiting) informal employment that avoids taxation plays an important role in thwarting the drainage of state’s finances. On the other hand formal employment and collective bargaining practices raise security on the workplaces by forcing the employers to adhere to standards and collective contracts that also guarantee a higher income and social security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The role of unions is also to include subordinate workers in civil society, so to allow them to participate in the dialectics with the political sphere as a collective unity, thus increasing their relative power in the interaction with hegemonic discourses. The democratic structure of its internal organization, with the election of worker’s representatives both as part of the union and in factory’s assemblies, strengthen the political awareness of their members and can induce them to get involved in political activities also out of the union. Defending interests and rights of the lower income subordinate workers has the goal to narrow income inequality so to promote social justice and improve self awareness of the subordinate classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main traits conventionally used to define a state-like structure are its autonomy from other organizations acting on the same territory, its centralized and formally coordinated structure and its monopolistic control of the means of coercion and tax collection. It may also be different from the Nation since this is one of the means of legitimization of a state. The main trait that distinguish a Nation is that its legitimizing discourse is based on a sense of commonality among its citizens, who share same cultural values, language and history. These traits can be pre-existent to the state or infused in the subjects to legitimize the same existence of the state as a political entity. So a Nation can be a consequence of a state-making process but its not necessarily the only one &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tilly_formation_1975&quot;&gt;(Tilly and Ardant 1975 pg 70)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we have conceptualized the state making as a process of imposing an organization’s structure over a territory, the means with which it imposes and legitimize its presence are the main characteristic that distinguish between different kind of regimes, from democracy to dictatorship. The role of civil organizations and social movements in the realization of “full” democracies and its correlations between civil freedoms are directly linked to the necessity for an autonomous condition of the civil society sphere. It is recognized that in cases of direct influence of state or political sphere on the social movements by funding, sponsorships or providing ideological basis, the outcome can lead to Dictatorial forms, like in Italy and Germany before the 2nd World War but also it can contribute to the formation of strong patronage regimes when state’s leaders achieve to co-opt informal actors &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;kwon_associations_2004 vine_african_1980&quot;&gt;(Kwon 2004; V. L. Vine 1980, &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;vine_nation-building_2008&quot;&gt;V. T. L. V. Vine (2008)&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the practice of state-crafting &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tilly_formation_1975&quot;&gt;(Tilly and Ardant 1975 pg 70)&lt;/span&gt; there are counteracting factors that can challenge the establishment of a hegemonic discourse. Studies in developing countries in Africa &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;vine_african_1980&quot;&gt;(V. L. Vine 1980)&lt;/span&gt; and ex-soviet Union &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tilly_social_2005 marat_state-crime_2006&quot;&gt;(Tilly 2005; Marat 2006)&lt;/span&gt; recognize the presence of a strong informal sector of the economy as part of the forces that challenge the centralization and monopolization of the political and economic sphere. Actors in paralegal or illegal sectors of economy can build strong parallel networks, based on patronage, a possible outcome for this can be the cooptation of these actors in state’s structure (as happened for example in Tajikistan) but also they can successfully substitute the “official” government in areas/regions were it lacks the necessary strength to impose its presence (as partially happened in Kyrgyzstan). These processes are mostly studied in developing countries because of the higher visibility they have during state and nation building processes. We can see some similarity also in well established states, as a consequence of the introduction of neoliberalist economic policies. Following the main points outlined in the Washington Consensus paper the privatization of important sectors, like welfare system and of strategic resources, introduced new actors in the political and economical sphere. The intrusion of informal networks based on clientelism substituting the state in providing social security can be a serious challenge to democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social movements are seen as main players in the process of democratization and nation building &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tilly_social_2005 ekiert_contentious_1998-1&quot;&gt;(Tilly 2005; Ekiert and Kubik 1998)&lt;/span&gt; (even if in many cases it would be better to refer to state crafting), in this paper I will focus on the role of labour unions in hindering the development of a strong informal sector by their mediation between the parts (workers and enterprises) and how this can prevent the dismemberment of state’s role along the application of neoliberalist discourses. In the specific case of Turkey I will scrutiny which role played the lack of strong unionism and integration between social movements in the cooptation of part of the Islamic civil society. Accordingly with Cihan Tuğal’s analysis &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tugal_passive_2009&quot;&gt;(see Tuğal 2009)&lt;/span&gt; this cooptation led to a redefinition of the hegemonic discourse exercised by the political sphere and eventually to a passive revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;shaping-contemporary-turkish-unionism&quot;&gt;Shaping Contemporary Turkish Unionism&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The history of labour unions in Turkey can be traced back to the early years of 19th century, and mostly it took the shape of mutual benefit institutions organized among different professions, in particular in state owned companies and with strong ties with socialist movements. Long hiatuses characterized the story of unionism in Turkey and shaped its situation in the present, the first one was in 1925 with the ban of all the political activities and the instauration of the single party regime, which lasted until 1946. Another distinctive trait of turkish labour unionism is its organization under umbrella institutions strongly tied to the government, as enunciated in the Associations Act of 1938 that was shaped on Mussolini’s corporatism and prohibited class based associations &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;aslan_f._and_baydar_trade_1998&quot;&gt;(Aslan and Baydar 1998)&lt;/span&gt;]. A new Act regulating labour and political associations was promulgated in 1947, that, although allowing the establishment of unions, prohibited protesting through strikes. In the following years the role of the unions grew constantly both in the number of members and in acts of protests, even declaring illegal strikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Democrat Party, who came to power in 1950 and was driven by a market oriented ideology, established new close relations with the U.S. and applied for the membership in the NATO. In 1952 one of the main unions in Turkey was founded: Turk Iş took the shape of an umbrella corporation meant to prevent the formation of strong class based associations of workers, strongly tied with the U.S. who were funding it from the very beginning. It also developed close ties with the leading party, as union members were granted parliamentary seats or prominent positions in public offices &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;nichols_global_2004-1&quot;&gt;(Nichols and Sugur 2004 pg 145)&lt;/span&gt;. After the military coup of 1960, a new constitution was signed granting basic freedoms for the labour unions, but it also included several limitations like the prohibition of political and general strikes. The main unions that are still active in contemporary Turkey were founded in this period. The success of collective protests organized by DISK, born by unions seceded from Turk Iş, increased the strength of worker’s movements and union membership grew through all the 1970s, as well as working hours affected by the protests &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;nichols_global_2004-1&quot;&gt;(Nichols and Sugur 2004)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation, though, worsened with the economic and political crises that led to the military coup of 1980: first the military junta banned all the federate and independent unions and then, in 1983, promulgated the new Trade Unions Act. Heavily restrictive measures meant to prevent the engagement of worker’s organizations in political activities and protests were adopted. The prohibition of collective bargaining in the public sector, to call for general strikes and the possibility for the government to delay or deny the permission to strike in case of emergency circumstances (obviously to be defined by the government itself) were some of the reforms introduced. Also new rules regarding application for membership were established, with a long and cumbersome procedure to comply to, that also required an expensive registration certified by a notary. The same rules were applied to resign from a union, and were especially effective to prevent the draining of members from accommodating unions, like for example the case of Turk Iş branch in the metallurgical sector (Türk Metal), where the procedure to join the union was included in the contract signed by the workers with the employer &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;nichols_global_2004-1&quot;&gt;(Nichols and Sugur 2004 pg 175)&lt;/span&gt;. Moreover the ban on the labour unions actually affected mostly the DISK, since the other two major unions were allowed again to operate soon after the coup: Turk Iş after few months and Hak-Iş (Islamic Federation) in 1981.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after the DISK came again in existence it faced the draining out of its former members and the imprisonment of its cadres, seriously undermining its effectiveness. The law ruling the possibility to participate in collective bargaining was in fact extremely restrictive, allowing only the unions representing at least 50% plus one of the employees in the workplace and 10% nationwide in the sector to be part of the negotiation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;private-sectors-main-unions-in-contemporary-turkey&quot;&gt;Private sector’s main unions in contemporary Turkey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;turk-iş&quot;&gt;Turk Iş&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founded in 1952 with the intention&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to establish new unions in those branches where no unions existed, to amalgamate the different unions in the same branch in each province, to combine trade unions in federations, to strive for the amendment of the Labour Code so as to cover all working people employed in industry, agriculture, commerce or elsewhere and to advocate the recognition of the right to strike to all workers. &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;aslan_f._and_baydar_trade_1998&quot;&gt;(Aslan and Baydar 1998)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has since its very foundation been strictly intertwined with the government and the TISK (the confederation of Turkish’ employers) as testified by many of its members who were elected in the parliament or appointed to government offices, and explicitly admitted to have received fundings from the U.S. and Turkish government during the 4th congress held in Ankara in November 1960. After the military coup in the ’80s, when was facing the challenge of the DISK, was the only union allowed to operate. As a consequence of its support to the military regime and the participation of its general secretary as Minister of Labour it was expelled from the ICFTU (International Confederation of Trade Unions). As of January 2009 it’s the biggest Turkish trade union with 2,239,341 members recorded officially by the statistics of the Ministry of Labour and Social Security &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;aslan_f._and_baydar_trade_1998&quot;&gt;(Aslan and Baydar 1998)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;disk&quot;&gt;DISK&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founded in the “golden age” of Turkish unionism (1960-1980), its core members were also part of the socialist oriented Workers Party of Turkey (TIP) and former members of Turk Iş, who during the strike in Pasabahce glass factory in 1966 formally seceded from Kristal-Iş (a branch of Turk Iş). The event that triggered the secession was the agreement with the TISK made by the union’s leadership who passed over the head of the workers involved in the protests. Gaining the support of other confederate unions Kristal-Iş members were able to resume the strike against the agreements signed by the confederate leadership and as a consequence were expelled. A new confederate treaty posed the basis for the foundation of DISK. In the statement released to explain the secession from the confederation it was claimed that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Türk-Is had become unable to implement its own principles, allowed a readjustment of the regulations on industrial branches in breach of international norms, lost its national identity and could only survive with American help, that it pursued a placatory policy that hindered workers in attaining their rights, opposed all justified strikes and supported the foundation of employer- friendly unions against Maden-Is. They declared that a new confederation was necessary to coordinate the struggle of individual unions for the common interests of the working people. The sole income of the new confederation would be workers’ dues and donations, and it would aim the establishment of a system of equality and fraternity in the country.&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;aslan_f._and_baydar_trade_1998&quot;&gt;(Aslan and Baydar 1998)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DISK leaders faced numerous convictions and trials in the early ’70s due to their autonomous position that let them pursue aims like increasing women’s rights on the workplace. After the military coup in 1980 its leaders were again arrested and the union was banned until January 1992, when the 8th general assembly was held, after that the union successfully joined ICFTU and ETUC and participated in the Democratic Platform with the other major unions. Nowadays DISK counts 426,232 members and is the third Turkish union considering the number of supporters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;hak-iş&quot;&gt;Hak-Iş&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founded in 1976 and posing as a mediator between employers and workers, Hak-Iş refuses communism, zionism and fascism and claim as its goal the establishment of harmonious relations in the workplace. Its religion based ideology is well testified by the the mosque inside a crescent drawn in its original symbol. After the military coup was one of the first union who was allowed to function again in 1981. Its relations with the National Salvation Party who governed as part of parliamentary coalitions let this union gain the support of the public sector related to the ministries under NSP’s control. In 1993 joined the Democratic platform from which withdrew after the other unions opposed its proposal to participate in the privatization of state owned enterprises on the basis that if they were to be sold they should have be in the hands of the workers. In 1997 joined ICTFU and ETUC. In 2009 it counted 431,550 members and was the second union in Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main feature of unionism in Turkey has been the constant attempt by the government to embed worker’s organization into the state apparatus in a corporate fashion, with strong reactions when the less restrictive law on Trade Union regulations and civil freedoms allowed the formation of links between social movements. What happened after the “golden age” of unionism of the “’60s and ’70s with the military coup in 1980 that disbanded all the independent organization is one example. The strong ties with the government and employers can therefore be considered at the basis of the actual predominance of Turk Iş. Its collusion with the state, with employers’ associations, and the ongoing clientelistic practices in its internal hierarchy in conjunction with legal constrains that effectively limit labour unions’ ability to operate can partially explain the contemporary disaffection of the workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;effectiveness-of-unions-in-contemporary-turkey&quot;&gt;Effectiveness of Unions in Contemporary Turkey&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first half of the ’90s witnessed a general resurgence of union activity and protests, thanks to the less restrictive laws and to the re-establishment of previously banned organizations like DISK. Also the three main unions representing public servants were founded. This is well reflected in the results of the World Values survey that in the aggregated table of the years between 1990 and 2001 records a cumulative 45,5% of positive answers (“quite a lot” and “great deal”) regarding people’s opinion on unionism and on the increasing number of participants in strikes that reached its peak in 1995 &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;nichols_global_2004-1&quot;&gt;(Nichols and Sugur 2004 pg 155)&lt;/span&gt;. The Democratic Platform was formed in 1993 with the goal to convey all the major unions’ efforts in collective bargaining. A general tendency of decreasing confidence in “effectiveness” and “importance of labour unions in affecting workers’ conditions” is then recorded from 2002 with an overall drop to 38,5% in the above mentioned positive answers to the World Values survey in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This overall tendency is paralleled by the decreasing coverage of collective bargained contracts, with the decline from 46.9% of workers covered in 1985 to 18.3% in 2004 &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;dinler_trade_2012-2&quot;&gt;(Dinler 2012 pg 10)&lt;/span&gt;.This numbers reflect the consequences of the Labour Law promulgated in 2003 that institutionalized fixed term and part time labour. The segmentation of labour force through the practice of subcontracting and job agencies that act as intermediaries between workers and employers poses another challenge to the labour unions as it is often difficult and cumbersome to understand which contract is applicable to the worker since there is a remarkable variation of the possible contexts of subcontracting thus leaving the workers in a sort of contractual limbo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is worth noticing that the laws regulating labour unions were the same approved under the military regime and lasted for 30 years. Just in 2012, on October 18th, a new law was promulgated which lowers the sector threshold to participate in collective bargaining to 3%, but keeps the workers’ representativeness in the workplace at 50% and the ban to general, political and solidarity strikes. Moreover it removes the payment for workers dismissed for joining a union in case of companies with less than 30 employees or for workers employed for less than 6 months. In conjunction with the lack of a maximum number of consequent term contracts this can leave the workers hired with the new regulations without protection. Public servants were allowed to organize in unions only after 1995 and in specific case like judges and policemen it is still forbidden. The recognition of collective bargaining was ratified in 2010, and only disputes on income are allowed. The decisions are to be taken between a Commission of public employers and a Central Commission of employees made of seven members appointed from the main unions accordingly to the rate of membership. It is not clear if the decisions are to be made with the majority of votes or it is sufficient the President’s approval, but since four out of six members plus the president are appointed from the most representative union (now the MEMUR-SEN, the closest to the government) the internal democracy of the Commission and subsequently the effective representativeness of public servants is strongly debatable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accordingly to the report drafted by ITUC in February 2012 &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;ituc_internationally_2012&quot;&gt;(ITUC 2012)&lt;/span&gt;, even if Turkey has ratified the eight core Labour Conventions, the country still doesn’t comply with the agreements signed. Regarding the case of workers’ and unions’ rights is stated that harassment against unionised workers is present in the workplaces and discrimination practices also with the use of violence are not enough discouraged by the existing laws and their application. Among the cases reported the most striking are those regarding judicial harassment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several trade unions have faced criminal charges under false or vague allegation, including setting up “terrorist organizations”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;many of them were sentenced to prison under these accusations, like 25 KESK members of Kurdish origins who were charged for “intellectual support to terrorist organizations” and convicted for six years, or the case of the union leader of KESK’s teachers branch who was threatened of dismissal after he denounced the use of child workers in Şanliurfa. Dismissals after unionisation in factories are common practice along with the pressure on workers to join more malleable and accommodating unions (or none at all) under the threat of mass firings and relocation of structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;islamic-unionism-and-turkeys-passive-revolution&quot;&gt;Islamic Unionism and Turkey’s Passive Revolution&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The changes in Hak-Iş policy and members composition can be emblematic of the processes that affected Islamic based social movements after the 1980 military coup. From its beginning this labour union focused on a religious basis for its ideology, in strong contrast with the other unions it posed itself in the position of offering a peaceful confrontation between employers and employees who are seen as part of the same Islamic community, and should therefore act in harmony. During the military regime this union soon supported the government and gained the possibility to start again its activism as early as the beginning of 1981. The main goals of the Islamic union have been to establish a feeling of brotherhood between workers and enterprises, and its main claims in the negotiations were about the creation of spaces dedicated to the prayers or to gain days off for pilgrimages. The turning point of the movement and the beginning of its inclusion into the dominant position can be traced soon after the end of the military regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the 4th general assembly Hak-Iş’s new leader Necati Çelik, elected in 1983, detached the union’s position from the Welfare Party, born from the ashes of MNP who was banned by the military, in 1986 also the idea of Islamic community as the basis for negotiations between employer-employees was deleted from the statute &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;duran_islamism_2005&quot;&gt;(Duran and Yildirim 2005)&lt;/span&gt;. The new direction improved the appeal of Hak-Iş among workers who previously were member of DISK. Ironically, and obviously thanks to the ongoing ban on DISK, during the late ’80s the once conservative and religious Hak-Iş was substituting the role of the most leftist union in Turkey. This change is further testified by Hak Iş’s new symbol which also incorporated a flywheel next to the crescent. With the expansion of its membership also its goals begun to get broader, for example supporting the claims for the improvement of civil rights and democratization, it took a further shift to more “traditional” union practices by organizing a general strike in 1991 and participating in the celebration of International Labour Day on the 1st of May of the same year. In the same period Hak-Iş assembly added the words “secularism” and “democracy” to its statute with the goal to obtain an international recognition by ICFTU and ETUC, achieving both of them in 1997. This interest in international relations also changed drastically its position about the admission of Turkey in the European Union, now actively supporting it. The last traces of syncretism between Islamic values and unionist practices took a shape similar to Islamic charities in Hak-Iş policies, promoting the provision of social services to workers, like healthcare and childcare. Also its way to deal with the privatization of state’s factories by buying them in the attempt to develop a model of employee-based ownership (in the shape of cooperatives) was an unconventional way to address the issue of increasing market hegemony. In this sense the transformations undertook by Hak-Iş after the military coup and the first introduction on neoliberalism in Turkey shaped it in the way of universal provisionism, encompassing all the spheres of social welfare that once belonged to the state:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hak-Iş might be considered the forerunner of the Muslim democratic leaning of the Justice and Development Party (AKP), which voices strong statements about the expansion of the sphere of politics regarding freedoms and human rights. AKP’s intention of joining European Union is again in parallel with Hak-Iş’s European inclinations &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;duran_islamism_2005&quot;&gt;(Duran and Yildirim 2005 pg 242)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the military coup of 1980 and the introduction of neoliberalism the aim of Islamic associations, networks and parties shifted to the realization of the concept of integral religion, an all-encompassing Islam, regulating people’s lives, trying to institute alternative lifestyles, places and economic relations. The same transformation in the political discourse of the Hak-Iş in conjunction with the declining role of unionism during late ’90’s can be read as part of an attempted adaptation to the application of neoliberalist policies and the subsequent commodization of everyday life, that established intertwined relations between market needs and the state through the political sphere and realized in the workplaces in the form of &lt;em&gt;market despotism&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paraphrasing Tuğal’s words &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tugal_passive_2009&quot;&gt;(Tuğal 2009)&lt;/span&gt;, how was possible that liberal neoconservatism appropriated bits and pieces of Islamic political society and civil society after 2002 to reinstitute the linkages of economy, civil society, political society and the state, and had as an outcome the absorption into the AKP of Islamist cadres and strategies?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tuğal’s interpretation the main actor in passive revolution’s reconstruction of hegemony is the sphere of political society that through its political leadership include (or &lt;em&gt;articulate&lt;/em&gt; using Tuğal’s terminology) social movements and organizations and creates a discourse of &lt;em&gt;authority&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;political unity&lt;/em&gt; legitimizing itself as hierarchical and at the same time encompassing the wholeness of the society through the expression of citizenship and community, embedding itself among the civil society. In the case of Turkey, its manifestation is the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AKP that has creatively blended Islam, tradition, supernaturalism, charisma and informality [..] to build an Islamic modernity &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tugal_passive_2009&quot;&gt;(Tuğal 2009 pg 22)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hegemony is defined as a process of articulating everyday life, spaces and economic relations by a certain leadership to create consent about its dominant position. Civil society, i.e. associations, social movements and informal networks that regulate everyday life, has to be linked to the state in this articulation to make possible the establishment of the consent that is at the basis of the hegemonic discourse. This connection is achieved by the political sphere, its immanency being at the intersection between civil society and state and by the discourse of citizenship used to legitimate the state’s apparatuses and hierarchies. The articulation between these three spheres has as its goal to subordinate state agencies to political control, and therefore at least partly to civil society. The degrees of overlapping between these actors have different consequences in the kind of regime that comes out as a result, the possibility of a democratic outcome is only one of them. Since the segmentation of civil society can lead to the inclusion of only a part of it in the hegemonic discourse, the result of this articulation can also be a populist and autocratic regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Labour union’s embeddedness with the civil society and other social movements has been studied on a cross country basis to search correlations with democratic governance. The result of this analysis is a strong positive relation between Government transparency, efficiency and response to citizen’s demands to the degree of connection between unions and civic organizations. Conversely:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;when unions are disconnected from middle-class and community based associations, the entire working class, or at least a segment of it is more likely to be co-opted by the state or the ruling block underpinned by either the landlord or capitalist class [..] the quality of state institution will be more likely to deteriorate under these circumstances &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;lee_labor_2007&quot;&gt;(Lee 2007 pg 605)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under particular conditions some sectors of the civil society can be merged to the state, giving birth to populist, autocratic or totalitarian regimes. This co-optation can be a reaction to an &lt;em&gt;organic crisis&lt;/em&gt; with which the hegemony changes its articulation to include new agent(s) to reiterate itself under changed and challenging circumstances. In this light we can argue that the historical development of corporatism and weak trade unions in Turkey can have played a major role in the lack of cohesion between civil society’s organizations and that this precondition allowed the co-opting of the Hak-Iş and MEMUR-SEN (or the Gülen movement) as part of this inclusion process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-aslan_f._and_baydar_trade_1998&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aslan, F., and O. Baydar. 1998. &lt;em&gt;Trade Unions in Turkey&lt;/em&gt;. Istanbul: Friedrich Ebert Vakfi. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fes.de/fulltext/bueros/istanbul/00253001.htm&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://www.fes.de/fulltext/bueros/istanbul/00253001.htm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-dinler_trade_2012-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dinler, Demet Şahende. 2012. “Trade Unions in Turkey.” Frıedrıch Ebert Stıftung. &lt;a href=&quot;http://heinonlinebackup.com/hol-cgi-bin/get_pdf.cgi?handle=hein.journals/intlr90&amp;amp;section=49&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://heinonlinebackup.com/hol-cgi-bin/get_pdf.cgi?handle=hein.journals/intlr90&amp;amp;section=49&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-duran_islamism_2005&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duran, Burhanettin, and Engin Yildirim. 2005. “Islamism, Trade Unionism and Civil Society: The Case of Hak-Iş Labour Confederation in Turkey.” &lt;em&gt;Middle Eastern Studies&lt;/em&gt; 41 (2): 227–47.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-ekiert_contentious_1998-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ekiert, G, and J Kubik. 1998. “Contentious Politics in New Democracies: East Germany, Hungary, Poland, and Slovakia, 1989–93.” &lt;em&gt;World Politics&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cjsonline.ca/pdf/contentiouspolitics.pdf http://journals.cambridge.org/abstract_S004388710000736X&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://www.cjsonline.ca/pdf/contentiouspolitics.pdf http://journals.cambridge.org/abstract_S004388710000736X&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-ituc_internationally_2012&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ITUC. 2012. “INTERNATIONALLY RECOGNISED CORE LABOUR STANDARDS IN TURKEY.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-kwon_associations_2004&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kwon, Hyeong-Ki. 2004. “Associations, Civic Norms, and Democracy: Revisiting the Italian Case.” &lt;em&gt;Theory and Society&lt;/em&gt; 33 (2): 135–66. &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/B:RYSO.0000023423.34384.88&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/B:RYSO.0000023423.34384.88&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-lee_labor_2007&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lee, Cheol-Sung. 2007. “Labor Unions and Good Governance: A Cross-National, Comparative Analysis.” &lt;em&gt;American Sociological Review&lt;/em&gt; 72 (4): 585–609.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-marat_state-crime_2006&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marat, Erica. 2006. &lt;em&gt;The State-Crime Nexus in Central Asia: State Weakness, Organized Crime and Corruption in Kyrgyzstan and Tajikistan (Silk Road Papers)&lt;/em&gt;. Institute for Security and Development Policy. &lt;a href=&quot;http://amazon.com/o/ASIN/B00379CDRY/&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://amazon.com/o/ASIN/B00379CDRY/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-nichols_global_2004-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nichols, Theo, and Nadir Sugur. 2004. &lt;em&gt;Global Management, Local Labour: Turkish Workers and Modern Industry&lt;/em&gt;. Palgrave Macmillan. &lt;a href=&quot;http://amazon.com/o/ASIN/1403917507/&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://amazon.com/o/ASIN/1403917507/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-tilly_social_2005&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tilly, Charles. 2005. “Social Movements, 1768-2004.” &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.citeulike.org/group/2546/article/781106&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://www.citeulike.org/group/2546/article/781106&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-tilly_formation_1975&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tilly, Charles, and Gabriel Ardant. 1975. &lt;em&gt;The Formation of National States in Western Europe&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 8. Princeton Univ Pr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-tugal_passive_2009&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuğal, Cihan. 2009. &lt;em&gt;Passive Revolution: Absorbing the Islamic Challenge to Capitalism&lt;/em&gt;. Stanford, Calif: Stanford University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-vine_nation-building_2008&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vine, Victor T Le VTL. 2008. “Nation-Building and Informal Politics.” &lt;em&gt;International Social Science Journal&lt;/em&gt; 59 (192): 155–67. doi:&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1468-2451.2009.00689.x&quot;&gt;10.1111/j.1468-2451.2009.00689.x&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-vine_african_1980&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vine, VT Le. 1980. “African Patrimonial Regimes in Comparative Perspective.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Modern African Studies&lt;/em&gt; 18 (4): 657–73. &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.cambridge.org/production/action/cjoGetFulltext?fulltextid=2517232&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://journals.cambridge.org/production/action/cjoGetFulltext?fulltextid=2517232&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/11/unions</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/11/unions</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Solidarity among strangers</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Reference: &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;candas_solidarity_2010&quot;&gt;(Candas and Bugra 2010)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shifting policies of solidarity are what the authors want to investigate in this paper: from a model of national identity based on the concept of turkishness to one based on the (supposedly) more encompassing religious identity of being sunni muslims. If the former posed the basis for the long lasting conflictual contrast of turkishness vs kurdishness, the latter looks more inclusive in its nature, based on the idea of islamic solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a general concept we can state that some sort of solidarity is found in every society, since it’s one of the bonds that keep a society together, it can be found indifferent forms, like a feeling shared by members of a group, a redistributive welfare system, a bond derived by some sort idea of common history or origin. Depending on the unit of analysis it assumes different natures, for example an ascriptive inclusive identity or a more insitutional fabric meant to hold society together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is introduced the main proposed division between the kind of solidarity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;two kinds of solidarity: “solidarity among strangers” which we will designate with the capital S, and other forms if solidarity informed by group interest or ascriptive identity, designed by small s. While both kinds of solidarity refer to a sense of belonging, feeling of togetherness and cooperation, the former has a normative priority over the latter. This is because S, without precluding the existing of ingroup solidarities, provides an inclusive framework that makes inter-group solidarity among strangers possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main argument of this paper is that S is a complex form of solidarity that can be realized and achieved only through a triangulated coexistence of liberty, equality and solidarity. Therefore is presented as part of a political process and born and achieved from political will:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S cannot be viewed as the outcome of an evolutionary process […] It is rather the political failures to acknowledge and meet the demands for individual rights that lead to a situation where S breaks down into soidarities based on sameness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The breaking down of these inter group bonds is then seen as a process which is started from a political failure but then it is bolstered by preexisting ingroup solidarities that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;further erode the ideals and institutions on which equal freedoms and democratic inclusion should ideally rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case sustained in the paper is that both Islamic solidarity and Kurdishness are forms of in-group solidarity generated as a consequence of the lacking of the above mentioned triangulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Ritter &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;ritter_irrational_1948&quot;&gt;(Ritter 1948)&lt;/span&gt; pre modern forms of solidarity (or as he calls them with a less controversial definition “irrational solidarities”) are based on shared identity and common historical descent. Bugra and Candas expand this conceptualization to state that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While solidarity among strangers prioritizes equal membership in a political community over ascriptive identities and thus refers to forging new bonds among strangers, this inclusive regime could nevertheless let other types of solidarities coexist along with the overarching citizenship identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The link between Solidarity and welfare regime transformation under neoliberalist policies is then explained as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The satisfaction of economic needs of the disadvantaged and their right to be recognized as equal members can either remain unmet, be transfered to voluntary and fickle benevolence or left to be satisfied through culturally informed practices within the closed community. […] (subsequently) the principle of equal freedom of all is seriously challenged in all cases where charity replaces formal rights based state transfers. […] In the case of particularly disadvantaged groups, such arbitrary and informal arrangements would necessarily exacerbate existing inequalities among the members of the wider society and widen the gaps among the communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The endogenous factor is the key element to explain a “cultural” shift to narrower forms of solidarity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;people who belong to different identity or interest groups might, at a particular historical juncture, begin to prioritize their ascriptive identity over the social bond defined in terms of inclusive democratic citizenship. […] not necessarily because people conceive of s as an aleternative to an already established S, but most likely because S is not available or failed and became delegitimized within that context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(again we see a link to economic crisis as also pointed out by Tugal &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tugal_contesting_2013&quot;&gt;(Tuğal 2013)&lt;/span&gt;, in this sense if it’s all about economic policies toward welfare and economic conjunctions we should expect something like Kondrateff’s waves in diffusion of solidarity and political polarization)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the pursuing of neoliberalist economic policies and the further delegation of welfare system to the sphere of civil society there is the risk of bolstering forms of solidarity than are based on ascriptive identity groups and not on rights of citizenship and equality, therefore while promoting initiatives of community empowerment to substitute social welfare these projects are at the same time undermining the bases itself for inclusive practices that are essential for a working democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this light we can see why understanding the processes on which different group styles are built is of primary importance to distinguish between “succesful” or outgoing bond creation and “unsuccesful” or in-group bonding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-candas_solidarity_2010&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Candas, Aysen, and Ayse Bugra. 2010. “Solidarity Among Strangers: A Problem of Coexistence in Turkey.” &lt;em&gt;Constellations&lt;/em&gt; 17 (2): 293–311. &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1467-8675.2010.00592.x/full&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1467-8675.2010.00592.x/full&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-ritter_irrational_1948&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritter, Hellmut. 1948. “Irrational Solidarity Groups: A Socio-Psychological Study in Connection with Ibn Khaldûn.” &lt;em&gt;Oriens&lt;/em&gt; 1 (1): 1. doi:&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.2307/1579028&quot;&gt;10.2307/1579028&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-tugal_contesting_2013&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuğal, Cihan. 2013. “Contesting Benevolence: Market Orientations Among Muslim Aid Providers in Egypt.” &lt;em&gt;Qualitative Sociology&lt;/em&gt; 36 (2): 141–59. doi:&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11133-013-9248-6&quot;&gt;10.1007/s11133-013-9248-6&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/10/solidarity-bugra</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/10/solidarity-bugra</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Contesting Benevolence</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Reference: &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tugal_contesting_2013&quot;&gt;(Tuğal 2013)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tugal’s view the double movement as expressed by Polanyi is a continuous struggle between hegemonic powers and counter hegemony that contraposes market economy and social groups, in his analysis conducted in sultanbeyli he sees how excluded strata of society get included in power relations based on clientelism in the act of realizing a passive revolution, pushing forward this interpretation he then analyzes benevolent associations to understand if and how these are part of the same cooptation by hegemonic powers or are part of the counter movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I argue that civil society menaces to undermine the double movement in the neoliberal age […] My findings corroborate critical literature that draws attention to the close linkage and mutual reinforcement between NGOs and neoliberalization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(but how does this cooptation work? is it an irrational attitude due to some form of adaptation to neoliberalist policies? is it a consequence of top down governmental policies?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently there is a strong correlation between the expansion of neoliberalist economic policies and the spread of charitable organizations, and he reads it with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a perspective that sees aid as reinforcing the dominance of powerful groups&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some associations ephasize on the individual respnsability for social exclusion and poverty, thus adhering to neoliberalist ideology (see also &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;isik_vakif_2014&quot;&gt;(Isik 2014)&lt;/span&gt;), and this leads the author to pose the main question: “&lt;em&gt;Do communitarian aid groups represent a counter-movement to marketization?&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can try to rephrase it for our own curiosity about civil society’s virtuous spyral as expressed by Putnam to: “do communitarian aid groups create succesful social bonds?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author categorize the associations oppoing their attitude toward the “professionality” required to deliver aid properly according to market economy and toward the responsibility of poverty, wether it’s on the poor themselves or to society and economic policies. This juxtaposition serves the purpose ot oppose market oriented charities to protection oriented ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;interestingly enough one ofthe interviewees explained the origin of poverty as the cutting of bonds between the poor and the better off:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The responsible persons severed their links with the poor (cfr pg 149)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-isik_vakif_2014&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isik, Damla. 2014. “Vakif as Intent and Practice: Charity and Poor Relief in Turkey.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Middle East Studies&lt;/em&gt; 46 (02): 307–27. doi:&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0020743814000129&quot;&gt;10.1017/S0020743814000129&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-tugal_contesting_2013&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuğal, Cihan. 2013. “Contesting Benevolence: Market Orientations Among Muslim Aid Providers in Egypt.” &lt;em&gt;Qualitative Sociology&lt;/em&gt; 36 (2): 141–59. doi:&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11133-013-9248-6&quot;&gt;10.1007/s11133-013-9248-6&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/10/Tugal-Aid</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/10/Tugal-Aid</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Notes from Democracy and Social Capital</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Reference: &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;warren_democracy_1999&quot;&gt;(Warren 1999)&lt;/span&gt;: Democracy and social capital by Eric M. Uslaner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of trust is central in a prosperous Democracy as it is a preminent part of what Putnam defined as social capital, and in Uslaner’s conceptualization is important as it sets moral values that are precurors of civic networks and social connectedness. Trust leads to cooperation by pushing people to behave morally and develop feelings of reciprocity to each other. The author makes a distinction between generalized and particularized trust, we can see several similarities with the concep of Solidarity vs solidarity as described by Bugra since he opposes trust only related to ones of your own kind vs trust towards a more generalized spectrum of people (the author is a bit vague in this distinction)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trust is then defined as a rational gamble, betting that on the long run there will be more benefits than relying only on one’s own self or on a kin-based small group of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to go beyond our kin and in-groups to trust a wide range of people, especially those whom we don’t know and who are different from us. Charitable contributions exemplify this dilemma. Voluntary giving heps make a community prosperous by reducing poverty and helping the underprivileged to make a fresh start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also repeats the concept of “bad associations” like KKK or similar exclusive groups as being based on a prticularized trust, thus not being included on the definition of social capital which is based and develops when relationships among individuals are based on a generalized trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people trust only their kind, they withdraw from civic life. […] As trust in others falls so does participation in civic activities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The television thesis proposed by Putnam to explain the ebbing of civic activism depends on the fact that time spent in front of the tv is the single biggest change in american society since the 50ies.. (but it doesn’t say why it is considered a cause and not a consequence) and as the author puts it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The generations raised on television […] became the new misanthropes. They are less trusting and join fewer voluntary organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Author’s analysis although this thesis seems to be unable to account for the change in civic activism as apparently some time of tv shows actually lead people to be more engaged. He then proposes optimism vs pessimism as a explanatory variable for trust, as there are relatively few distrusting optimists as well as few trusting pessimists (this looks almost a tautology to me as we defined trust as a bet for long run benefits so obviously who ahs faith in the future would think that there are better odds at winning betting on trust than who hasn’t, also definition of being optimist as posed by the author seems to imply some feelings and attitudes that alread encompass the concept of trust as being part of being optimists).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first consequence of optimism being so closely related to trust is that when the future looks bleak (as for example during an economic crisis or when income inequality increases) trust makes less sense for the ones that are worse off in society, increasing greatly the risk in “loosing the long run gamble on trust” (does this leads us to expect waves of trust and solidarity following the example of Kondrateff’s waves?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About the correlation between democracy and trust the Author argues that there is no proof that trust can build democracy nor that democracy can build trust, while at the same time authoritarian regimes are proven to have to destroy civil society to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But “&lt;em&gt;To have a democracy does not mean that you have a well functioning government. Societies that are badyl polarised by class or ethnic divisions may have democratic constitutions but they won’t work well as deocracies.&lt;/em&gt;” This argument is compelling since we should not just focus on defining democracy purely on a legal and constitutional system but also looking at the quality of the democratic environment. This is because as we are obesrving nowadays there is an apparently strong correlation between the lack of trust in well developed democracies and the rise o populist and sectarian politicians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-warren_democracy_1999&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warren, Mark, ed. 1999. &lt;em&gt;Democracy and Trust&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge, UK ; New York: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/10/Democracy_and_social_capital</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/10/Democracy_and_social_capital</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Notes from Elusive Togetherness</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Reference: &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;lichterman_elusive_2005&quot;&gt;(Lichterman 2005)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Putnam’s study on civil society in Italy and in America we see how civic group membership has been dropping since 1960s, Lichterman argues that the concept of social capital is not fully adequate to address the issue at hand. In his argument Liechtermann sustains that it’s also important to look at the kind and the different meanings of ties that civic groups can build and how these ties can “contribute to a greater civic togetherness in America”. In his words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal was to understand how different meanings that group gave to ties might influence the relationship they could create as they reached beyond the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also draws a distintion between the political analysis of social problems and the set of customs and practices employed to address them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned that volunteering often did not build community [..] cultural customs played a subtle, important role in making a broader togetherness elusive for most of the groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the idea of participation in civic groups as decribed by Alexis de Tocqueville these have been seen as playing a prominent role in bolstering social solidarity and building a greater community (“&lt;em&gt;local workshops of social solidarity&lt;/em&gt;”). But as the author noticed during his fieldwork this assumption is not necessarily and always true, two of the three groups he observed couldn’t eventually create those ties with the broader community, not even among themselves as the groups and meetings were discontinued. So the natural question that arises from this observation is, how the group that succeeded was different from those who failed? To which degree the interactions between groups’ members influenced the chance of success of spiraling outwards to build greater social ties?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two main questions are addressed by this study:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The social spiral argument, which states that as individuals join civic groups they &lt;em&gt;tend to&lt;/em&gt; create enduring relationships with other group’s members as well as with other individuals who they wouldn’t have met under normal circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Broader ties cultivated by civic groups help to empower civil society, ultimately increasing the collective decision-making responsibilities people carry in their capacity as citizens&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the arguments of this book is to propose that the meanings of the social ties built matter at least as much as the ties themselves. A secondary one is “&lt;em&gt;how people bring religion into public life&lt;/em&gt;” and how religion might influence the ways individuals interact (the groups’ cutsoms, or customary practices) during groups’ activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Putnam’s argument “social capital” is made of three elements: - social networks - norms of reciprocity - trust&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decline in participation to civic groups is worrying because it is supposed to create social capital, and consequently it bolster civic consciousness enlarge inter group and inter community ties and increases the possibility for citizens to hold governemnt accountable for it actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his theory, social networks can be divided by two kinds of social capital, the first one being the “bonding”, that is infra group cohesion, the second instead “bridging” the same cohesion between different groups, only the latter creates a successful social spiral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One criticism to this is that the category is so broad that don’t let us analyze it in a critical perspective to understand which actions as well which systemic conditions (i.e. institutional and social) can actually promote social capital. Another important point of criticism regards the circularity of the concept, as a group’s actions promote its social capital but at the same time are part of it, and might appear in some way a tautology in this sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other sociologists observed that civic groups can also create social tunnels instead of social bridges, thus hindering cohesion among citizens, when they are more focused on their members’ shared interests preventing them to actively join and participate in civil society as a whole. According to Jason Kauffman civic groups can build moats instead of bridges (cit. pg 29) as he noticed in civic clubs based on different backgrounds and ethnicities that were increasing differences. Neo-Tocquevillians’ defense against this argument is that this kind of civic groups can be considered an outlier, and exception to the norm that belongs to some sort of dark side of civil society. But this approach can’t answer and is not productive in addressing the main question of how and what let a civic group to start the social spyral, especially refusiong to analyze the different dynamics of different groups removing some of them &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; from the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So one of the main question under scrutiny here is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is casual, serial vounteering a good indicator of social capital? (pg 82)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the author puts it,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the relationships that constitute social capital sustain a “regular connection among individuals” (Putanm 2000), and is comprised of relationships in which people are “doing with” others. (ibidem)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acceptive passively that any kind of volunteering and associationism creates and bolster social capial has also the implicit consqeuence of regarding any kind of relationship and dynamic developed by volunteers and recipient as a “reguar connection”, and doesn’t analyze its very own nature. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volunteering in a loosely connected network [..] did not teach us how to create more enduring bridges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question of reflexivity revolves around two key issues, firstly about not investigating ourselves how we act and what drives our actions and secondly about not being able to include difrerent point of views in the discussion thus thwarting the possibility to actualy reach out to a variety of individuals that although are interested in the general topic offer a different reading of it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the success of a program whose main goal is to build “bridges” between individuals can’t simply be measured by its material outcome, especially since it might be reached more succesfully by providing some sort of moral support, or “helping the families in small practical ways” (cit. pg 135) that can hardly be accounted for but that might might succeed better in creating enduring connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, in the case about “adopt a family” program the lack of reflexivity didn’t let the volunteers bridge the gap between them and the families they were trying to help, thus prventing categorizing the ‘poor’ in any other way than their own preconcieved ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thouthgfully sensitive to &lt;em&gt;differences&lt;/em&gt; between their families and themselves, the volunteers did not ove from sensitivity to active, reflective curiosity about a biger social world that made “differences” into inequalities, as well as barriers to communication (pg 137).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One criticism is that apparently evangelical groups’ course of action relentelessy rely on the self centered idea that personal action can be sufficnent to address the adressee’s situations one by one ameliorating them just by the strength of the connection, thus leaving out the principal outcome for a positive engagement of civic groups, that is to create bridges, or as Tocqueville put it the positive spiral to social cohesion. This approach is reflected not only in the diffuculties the volunteers face when approaching ‘their’ families but also in the social interactions among group’s memebers among themselves, that are described by the author as ‘awkward’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charity imposed from outside may count as a kind of bridge relationship if the charity is accepted and endures over time, but it hardly empowers social self-orgnization the way Tocquevillians would hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-lichterman_elusive_2005&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lichterman, Paul. 2005. &lt;em&gt;Elusive Togetherness: Church Groups Trying to Bridge America’s Divisions&lt;/em&gt;. Princeton Studies in Cultural Sociology. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/09/notes-elusive</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2016/09/notes-elusive</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Non profit law in Turkey</title>
				<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;notes-on-non-profit-law-in-turkey&quot;&gt;Notes on Non profit law in Turkey&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;file-at-httpccss.jhu.edupublications-findingsdid423&quot;&gt;file at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://ccss.jhu.edu/publications-findings/?did=423&quot; class=&quot;uri&quot;&gt;http://ccss.jhu.edu/publications-findings/?did=423&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turkish legal tradition has to be interpreted within the &lt;em&gt;civil law&lt;/em&gt; tradition of european tradition. (main difference from the &lt;em&gt;common law&lt;/em&gt; used for example in the US is that precedents can’t be accepted as a primary source of law).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;thus in Turkey the main body of laws regarding NPOs is mostly found in the body of private law. But since there are disparate categories of entities that can be considered as NPOs in turkish legislation: unions, chambers and professional organizations, associations, foundations and cooperatives the actual regulations are scattered across the private and public branches.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2015/12/NP-Law-Turkey</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2015/12/NP-Law-Turkey</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Nonprofit Notes</title>
				<description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes-on-the-working-paper-from-johns-hopkins-comparative-nonprofict-sector-project&quot;&gt;Notes on the working paper from Johns Hopkins Comparative Nonprofict Sector Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;see-the-paper-online&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://adm-cf.com/jhu/pdfs/CNP_Working_Papers/CNP_WP24.pdf&quot;&gt;see the paper online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the increasing recognition of third sector organizations as part of economic growth and their preminent role in democratization processes and in welfare provision, the study and subsequently the comprehention of the inner mechanisms and specificities of nonprofit organizations&lt;a href=&quot;#fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnoteRef&quot; id=&quot;fnref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; remain poorly understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three levels of study are recognized as not yet fully delevoped:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The basic &lt;em&gt;descriptive&lt;/em&gt; information is lacking, as it seems that in the developing countries there is a systematic lack of recording of such activities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the &lt;em&gt;conceptual&lt;/em&gt; level there is a scarce understanding of a multifarious landscape of organizations that encompass religious schools, human rights organizations grassroots movements and many more. Approaching such a differentiated context requires proper analitycal tools, and the overuse of the categorization based on NGO vs Non-NGO even if someway useful might be misleading, especially in the under-representation of the role of “informal” or religion based organizations, thus preventing a proper comprehension.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;theoretical&lt;/em&gt; framework with which scholars approach the study of third sector in developing countries is mostly biased by its own origin in the study of the Western context, thus suffering from forms of “orientalization” and from scarcity and inadequacy of useful analytical categories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selection of case countries: criterias&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Low per capita income: one of the arguments ofthe aper is to understand how average income influence the development of third sector organizatios, and to pursue this goal countries in the lowest range of average per capita incoma are selected so to differentiate from westarn high average income countries. The idea is that &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; alone can’t bolster the growth of such organizations, especially since financial, time and organizational resources and skills are needed. The leading theory for this is drawn from &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;weisbrod1977&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;weisbrod1977&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;: &amp;gt;such organizations are most likely to emerge not where resources are uniformly limited, but where heterogeneous needs emerge and some peoplehave the resources to resopond to these needs through joint action.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Small Urban Middle Class: rurality is one of the criteria for selection of case studies, as urban population and middle class is considered to be directly correlated with the birth and growth of non profit institutions (to support this theory the paper quotes &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;salamon1994&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;salamon1994&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;moore1967&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;moore1967&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Authoritarian political regimes: with the due differences every selected country had experienced some form of authoritarian regime, and this is another factor that influence negatively the development of third sector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Correlation between social welfare spending and third sector development: there are two major theories that relate the two phenomena, the first one &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;weisbrod_voluntary_1977&quot;&gt;(Weisbrod 1977)&lt;/span&gt; proposes an inverse relation between the two arguing that third sector is a form of reaction and adaptation to a fault in the redistribution system managed by the state, while the second sees the two as complementary due to having opposite strengths and weaknesses thus arguing in favor of a reciprocal &lt;em&gt;empowerment&lt;/em&gt; of the two &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;salamon_partners_1995&quot;&gt;(Salamon 1995)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Religion&lt;/em&gt;, since there is a strong correlation betwen religion and nonprofit activity (the reasons could be different from case to case, varying from sentiments of altruism and means to attract new followers).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-salamon_partners_1995&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salamon, Lester M. 1995. &lt;em&gt;Partners in Public Service: Government-Nonprofit Relations in the Modern Welfare State&lt;/em&gt;. JHU Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-weisbrod_voluntary_1977&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weisbrod, Burton Allen. 1977. &lt;em&gt;The Voluntary Nonprofit Sector: An Economic Analysis&lt;/em&gt;. Lexington Books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn1&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;this term is used interchangeably for all those activities who are part of the third sector, including fb-ngo, ngo and so on&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2015/12/nonprofit-notes</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2015/12/nonprofit-notes</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Nation Building in Ottoman Empire</title>
				<description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper I’m going to discuss and present Ottoman Empire’s policies in its goal to incorporate nomadic tribes in its society, this aim was pursued in different ways through time, adapting strategies accordingly to the context. Beginning from the Tanzimât Era, the Ottoman Empire attempted various reforms to resist the disintegration processes it was facing. The declining central authority tried to revive its power modernizing the military and bureaucratic apparatus and reforming the tax revenue system, in particular the latter was performed performing the first census and cadastral survey. One of the main issues that the Empire had to face was the ethnic and social segmentation that produced a centrifugal force among the population, although we have to wait for the article 8 in the 1876’s constitution to have a clear statement about Ottoman Citizenship, we can trace back to the Tanzimât Fermânı, where the Sultan extended and granted equal rights (but also equal duties) to the entire population of the Empire, a first idea to overcome the danger of social dismemberment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The long attempted sedentarization and acculturation of the nomadic tribes dwelling the Empire, that before Gülhane Edict had mainly economic and security purposes, were thus pursued in the new light of transforming them into citizens. Besides the ongoing problem of tax evasion, the main economic challenges nomads posed to the Empire were three-folded: the pillaging raids &lt;em&gt;reduced producers’ ability to pay taxes fear of raids diminished economic productivity by reducing the area under cultivation and restricting trade; and the cost of providing security forces to deter raiding was high, while such forces were only intermittently successful against the more mobile tribes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan_frontiers_1999&quot;&gt;(Rogan 1999)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan_frontiers_1999&quot;&gt;(Rogan 1999 pg 84)&lt;/span&gt;. Also the capability to literally substitute the Empire as social and political organizations in the peripheries dangerously undermined its territorial integrity. Urban population and especially statesman and bureaucrats shared a common vision of the nomadic tribes, almost the same adjectives are used in describing their way of life: ranging from savage, ignorant and wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every word can be referred to the contrast between the modernization ideas proposed by Sultan Abdülmecid I and the backwardness of the periphery. The civilizing mission of the Ottoman Empire thus finds its own moral excuse in pursuing what is a purely political and economical project. In a certain way this attitude resemble the famous statement by Massimo D’Azeglio: &lt;em&gt;Unfortunately, we have made Italy, but we didn’t make Italians&lt;/em&gt; pronounced after Italy’s unification and referring both to the cultural and linguistical differences in the population but also to the necessity to acculturate and modernize the people living in the country. The main argument of this paper is then to analyze the shift from inclusion of population through territory to the inclusion of territory through population during the late Ottoman Empire focusing especially on the case of Transjordan nomadic tribes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;definitions&quot;&gt;Definitions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peculiar context of Ottoman Empire requires attention both regarding the historical setting and the methodological tools that are going to be used in this analysis: the terminology used is to be defined not from a qualitative but on a quantitative and neutral perspective to avoid misinterpretations, also the origin of most of the concepts can lead to a biased explanation. Describing the last years of the Ottoman Empire scholarly literature has used the terms of modernization, nation-state, colonialism (or neo-colonialism), that were usually meant to be applied in the transformations that happened in Europe starting from the 16th century. Therefore if we want to borrow these concepts we have first to understand how they can fit into the context of our study. In the Ottoman case the territorial integrity and the presence of the state in the peripheral regions, here meant as borderlands with neighboring countries as well as all these areas were the friction &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;scott_art_2009&quot;&gt;(Scott 2009)&lt;/span&gt; of terrain prevented a strong ad effective rule by the Ottoman authorities, is characterized by the lack of a strong centralized rule and the presence of peculiar policies of live and let live with the local authorities that are functional to its own existence. The so called modernization introduced after the Gulhane edict is to be intended as a process of strong centralization by reducing the political distance between the center and the above mentioned peripheries, this was accomplished by strengthening the presence of state’s bureaucrats and functionaries and their relative power regarding the local hierarchies and political structures. The idea &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tilly1990coercion&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;tilly1990coercion&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; that the centralization processes happened in Europe are correlated to the need of increasing the wealth extraction and coercive power of the states regarding their subjects in their struggle for survival as political autonomous entities that characterized the Middle Ages and the Modern History, let us introduce a neutral interpretation of modernization meant as an increase in the efficiency of the state’s apparatuses; the correlation between this process and the development of Nation-states in Europe doesn’t take into account, though, the well established power relations and policies of legitimating Ottoman power that were already present in all the regions under the Empire’s control, and also overrides its multifarious nature regarding ethnic composition and religious practices.This is in neat contrast to the “birth” and development of Nation states in European context since they all faced before or along the process of centralization a parallel attitude of creating a mono ethnic and religious setting inside their borders.&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tilly1990coercion mann2004dark&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;tilly1990coercion&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;; &lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;mann2004dark&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; So, to which extent can we apply the concepts of nation and nation building to the case of Ottoman Empire? First of all we have to define the ideas at their basis: Nation is usually defined as a community of people sharing common language, culture and history, that are aware of this unity even if there is no actual political realization, and traditionally seen as a preexisting entity and justification for the realization of a State-Nation especially by the national movements during the 19th century. But reversing this last statement we can also say that &lt;em&gt;Two men are of the same nation if and only if they recognize each other as belonging to the same nation. In other words, nations maketh man; nations are the artefacts of men’s convictions and loyalties and solidarities.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;gellner2006nations&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;gellner2006nations&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 6)&lt;/span&gt; in this light we can also conceptualize the process of nation building as an attempt pursued by political or intellectual elites to make a territorial unity overlap with the population living in it under a shared idea of commonality thus an actively pursued program by the political power. Under this light, the concept of state-building is fittest to the Tanzimât Era since it in Tilly’s terms consists in: &lt;em&gt;consolidation of territorial control, differentiation of government from other organizations, acquisition of autonomy, [..] centralization and coordination.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tilly1975formation&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;tilly1975formation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 70)&lt;/span&gt; that describes quite well the transformations introduced in the bureaucratic apparatus. Conversely the idea of nation-building is more directed to the establishment of a collective sense of community among the population. So the development of a Nation state is just one of the possible outcomes of the centralization and state crafting process but not a necessary and direct consequence. Therefore if we want to understand if the Empire’s policy of inclusion regarding nomad tribes can be assimilated in some way to the process of nation building, we’ll have to analyze in which ways the settlement and acculturation programs were pursued and their transformations during time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;ottoman-expansion-in-transjordan&quot;&gt;Ottoman expansion in Transjordan&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The control of Transjordan was seen as necessary by Ottoman rulers for its strategical position as the main route to reach Arabian peninsula and the holy cities of Islam on the pilgrimage path. The fertile and mostly unused lands in the region also were considered as a unused asset of the Empire, a luxury that wasn’t acceptable in a period were the central government’s revenues were drastically decreasing due to the loss of the European provinces. The penetration into the inner lands of southern Syria began officially in 1851 with the establishment of an administrative centre in Irbil, the formal excuse was to protect villagers and farmers from the pillages carried on by the Sirhan and Bani Kilab tribes, goal successfully achieved by the Ottoman army. While this proof of strength established a first presence in the area, subsequent attempts to build more permanent solutions were deemed to failure, like the Algerian refugees colony that didn’t last after 1852, and a peasant’s rebellion in May of the same year that drew out the direct Ottoman influence for other twelve years. In 1864 the Vilayet law of provinces’ reform offered another justification for the intrusion of Ottoman’s officers in the region, with the appointment in 1866 of a new Governor in Damascus who had as his primary goal to aplly the new laws: after securing Ottoman’s position in the North, Mehmet Raşid begun a campaign in Southern Tranjordan 1867 through the ’Ajlun and then in the Balqa’ area. The region’s tribes were led by the ’Adawan, and the expedition against them was a unprecedented success; after the attempt to take control again on the region by the leading tribes, a second campaign stated the prominent role of the Ottomans.The intention to enter Arabian Peninsula from Transjordan led the campaign of 1872 to include Ma’an into the administrative region, but the costs of establishing a new administrative centre there were so high compared to the revenues that it was shut down in 1873. After the British Empire conquered Egypt (1882) a new security concern about Ma’an’s strategic position as a buffer area was at the base of proposals to create again an administrative unit in the city, but even if the governor renewed his requests along all the 1880s it remained unattended by the Sultan. Given the small population of Ma’an the main interests of Ottoman officers shifted to the bigger city of Karak where, after facing a strenuous resistence that was overcome mostly with negotiation and the exchange of gifts, they achieved to permanently establish a new administrative outpost to extend the Empire’s influence directly into the southernmost area of Syria. Already in 1868 the governor of Salt was expressing about the necessity to educate the children of the “savage” population in the light of the reforms, and, although most of the officers appointed in the regions were Turks who had served the Empire long before being sent to the turbulent Transjordan provinces, many of them were able to speak Arabic and therefore were able to negotiate with the local authorities &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg. 56)&lt;/span&gt;. After imposing its presence with military strength Ottoman Empire was changing its inclusionist policies to conquer the heart of the population. The main means to achieve this goal were to improve the infrastructures and standardized systems of measure to improve economy, to appoint rightful officers limiting corruption and collusion, and thus stimulating in the local ethnicities a sense of membership as part of the Empire. Especially the building of schools and structures to be used by the collectivity was seen with enthusiasm by the local population and gave a sign of the benefits of being Empire’s subjects. Among the few documents testifying administrative practice in Transjordan, there’s the evidence of the good memories left behind by Tahir Bey Badirkhan who actively sought to improve the conditions of Irbil, the city he was appointed to in 1882, by rebuilding the old mosque and a primary school but also solving the hydric supplies problems of the city by draining and cleaning the canals and the water tanks. Obviously not only public buildings were necessary to prove the Empire’s presence but administrative structures were planned and built to efficiently carry the basic tasks imposed by the Tanzimât reforms, like applying the rule of law and tax extraction: for example between 1874 and 1889 in Salt were erected the Governor’s residence and Government office housing the local court and the district’s prison &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 61)&lt;/span&gt;. Even if the grandeur of the buildings was related to the centre’s importance also in the smallest towns were built smaller structures carrying the Sultan’s symbols to testify the presence of the ruler in all the villages of the province. As a consequence of this expansion in previously semi-autonomous regions one of the tasks to be accomplished was to effectively link the villages to the administrative centres and these to the regional chief town. In the first years the establishment of a network of roads was more related to the needs of the villagers for farming and trading purposes, but along with the increasing presence of Empire’s officers and structures, projects of improvement of the roads and communication infrastructures were carried on in a more centralized form. The establishment of the first telegraph line in south Syria was ordered by Sultan AbdulhamidII in 1892 and the first telegraph was sent on 6th January 1901 &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 64)&lt;/span&gt;, the line was extremely important both in stating the Empire’s presence but also in providing its subjects with means to easily and successfully send petitions to the centre, the necessity to protect the lines and poles also had the side effect of including the bedouins as guards of the lines by providing monthly wages to the shaykhs to prevent damages to the lines from their tribes’ members. Conversely the role played by the Hijaz railway reduced the income of the tribes on its path, before the building of the railway their economic activities were supplemented by renting camels and get paid by the officer s to guarantee a safe passage to pilgrims, thanks to the railway the need for both services constantly decreased and the shaikhs had to be pleased by lower monthly wages for the protection of the rails. Another consequence of the improvement of the means of transportation with the building of paved roads, ferry lines and railways was to increase the speed of deployment of troops while decreasing the costs of the expeditions, this combined with the government structures that hosted prisons and police stations with a permanent presence of armed force in the villages was to impose the Empire’s “monopoly of violence” in the region. In this context the military presence increased the chances of success in negotiations with the tribes, therefore the improved security resulted also by the application of the laws provided the necessary setting for a general increase in trade and economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;settlement-program-and-the-land-law&quot;&gt;Settlement program and the Land Law&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The struggle to survive as a territorial and political unity against the increasing pressure of European countries in 19th century was one of the main factor that forced Ottoman Empire to begin considering an optimization of its internal unused resources in terms of land, revenues and military conviction. Tribes’ settlement has always been of fundamental importance for the Empire to assess its predominance in the areas dwelt by nomadic tribes. Since this interactions are of a two-way nature there was mutual influence and adaptation; the policies to approach the nomadic problem were geopolitically diversified, for example tribes living in border or in inaccessible areas were usually granted more autonomy than the ones dwelling core regions, because the cost and the difficulties to conduct extensive military operations against these population left this option as a last resort. State tribe dialectics were also dependent on the inside structure of the latter, since in the concept of “nomadic tribe” are included very different kind of social structures, from highly hierarchical to almost egalitarian ones, also the dispersion and the extent of the region actually used for grazing and transhumance patterns are an important distinctive factor that influenced Empire’s policy and effectiveness. Summarizing, have been recognized three main factors influencing Ottoman state’s strategies&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;Koksal2006&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;Koksal2006&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Geopolitical location&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Geographical boundedness, i.e. the degree of dispersion of different households&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Internal organization, i.e. the degree of hierarchical complexity&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some kind of correlation between these variants: usually the higher the n2 the higher the n3. The n1 obviously is dependent on geographical position and on state’s relations with neighboring countries. Previous studies recognized four main strategies deployed by the Ottoman Empire to control and settle the tribes present in its territory up to the Tanzimât Era, mostly they’re not of coercive nature and are: exile and military intervention, enclosing the tribe in a semi autonomous area and limit the intervention of the state just to collect tributes, including the local leaders providing them arms and resources to help maintaining their rule and the use of trade and land allocation to willingly include the population in a chosen area&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;Koksal2006&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;Koksal2006&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; Since the Empire was still expanding its territories there was abundance of land to colonize, so the coercive practice of forced exile and the incentive to settle into allocated lands were a common practice to pacify conflict situations between nomads and sedentary populations. Both of them were part of the process to occupy new lands, settled populations usually were stimulated to move to new lands with assignments, in the case of nomads tax exemptions to settle along trade routes and watchtowers to protect them or in extreme cases forced exile were common methods. As the Empire stopped expanding and entered into a financial crisis the forced exile method was used more and more often to solve internal conflicts especially in the inner areas, along the borders some sort of autonomy was granted by selecting local leaders as interlocutors and providing them with financial and military support in case of needing. The authority of local leaders backed up by the Empire relied on their ability to collect taxes from their population and to keep quiet relations with the settled communities. Beginning with the Tanzimât Era we can observe a drastic change in the pursuing of the settlement policy backed by the ideas at the very basis of the edict. The concepts of equal rights and duties for all, Muslim and non-Muslim: the guarantee for life, honor and private property, equal taxation and military service together with the idea of a centralized bureaucratic administration pushed to important consequences as the first cadastral survey that begun in 1858 was also followed by a nation wide census to record all male inhabitants present in the Empire and provided them with a tax certificate that also had the purpose of an identification paper. For the first time the Ottoman state attempted a mass scale settlement program: before 1839 as we have seen sedentarization was used to solve contingent issues, but with the new impulse: &lt;em&gt;Regardless of whether they were a source of disruption or not, tribes in several areas, including Bosnia, Kurdistan, Syria and Transjordan were forced or encouraged to settle permanently in their respective regions&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;Koksal2006&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;Koksal2006&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 477)&lt;/span&gt; Still until 1860s the term used referring to the policies regarding nomads was te’dib, that implies a form of violence and suppression, but then it was substituted in the documents with istimalet, that refers to an approach meant to gain the good will of the protected&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;Avci2009&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;Avci2009&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;. This change in the approach on nomadic issues is reflected also in the formalization of another way to push the nomads to regularize their relations with the state by the approval of the Land Reform that was put in the agenda of Ottoman officers from 1858. As a consequence the pastoral economy was to be modified as the state closed the migration routes and imposed the registration of land and livestock properties. The application of the Land Reform prevented nomadic tribes to register their lands since they weren’t able to meet the two basic requirements to claim ownership: demonstrating with receipts to have paid taxes on them or to have carried farming activities for the last three years. This situation allowed the creation of new villages on “unused” lands by settling refugees and farming tribes, one good example of this outcome is testified in the controversy between Sattam Fayiz and the Christian ’Uzayzat tribe on the land surrounding the ruined village of Madaba, after a dispute with a Muslim tribe in their home town of Karak, the ’Uzayzat were pushed by the local missionaries to move in the Balqa region, after a survey they found a suitable place in Madaba. This village was considered by Sattam Fayiz, leader of the Bani Sakhr tribe, as part of his domains, therefore he threatened the Christians to force them to go away from his lands. But the ’Uzayzat, keen on inter tribal politics, had an agreement with the Bani Hamida tribe for mutual protection thus preventing Sattam Fayiz to realize his threats. The only option left for him was so the application of a complain to the Ottoman Governor claiming the lands object of the controversy as his possession and then forcing the Christians to return to Karak. But the Governor at that time was Midhat Paşa, whose main goal was to double the tax income of the province by settling unused lands therefore he supported ’Uzayzat’s colonization of Madaba for farming purposes. When the leader of the Bani Sakhr wasn’t able to produce neither the documents stating his tax payments nor to demonstrate that he farmed the land in the last three years &lt;em&gt;Midhat Paşa instructed the regional governor in Nablus you should give as a reply to Sattam Fayiz’s claims to these and any other lands that he has no right to lands not cultivated.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 81)&lt;/span&gt; This movements of population eroded the interstices of unused lands between villages by creating new settlements and establishing new administrative units as we have seen in the case of Beersheba, leaving less and less territories to be exploited by nomads to graze their herds but also narrowing the distance between them and the centres of Ottoman power. Along and as a reaction of the land grants for the foundation of new colonies to refugees and other settled communities, nomadic tribes begun petitioning the government asking recognition for their lands on a legal basis. Favourable conditions to induce the nomads to accept the new land regime were ordered by the government, like the exemption from the 10% tax on the estimated value of the land registered, and lower fees on the registration costs. The success of this policy can be seen in the fact that as early as 1879 the first land register on the Salt area was completed, twelve years before the opening of the registration office in Salt. Since patterns of private properties or rights similar to ownership were already present both in farming communities and in tribesmen the main difficulties left to the Ottoman officers were how to “translate” them in the categories present in the law, in the process it appears that the bureaucrats left most of the agreements on communal lands and on the names on which to register the ownerships to the local hierarchies, focusing in adapting the different cases to the law’s standardized categories. This produced as outcome some variations in how the properties were registered, for example the Bani Sakhr tribe divided the land between the more important families, while in other tribes like the ’Adwan, ’Abbad and Balqawiyya all the tribesmen were assigned their share of land. Established hierarchies were probably an important factor in differentiating these pattern of registration, since the Bani Sakhr were the largest tribe in the region and their shaykhs the less settled, still relying mostly on herding for their income, and the most powerful, the others were more related with settled communities as we have seen with the mutual protection agreement that the Bani Hamida and the ’Abbad tribe dealt with the Christian community in Madaba and less hierarchical&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;. The overall result of the application of the Land Reform was positive for the tribes in the region, since almost all the unsettled lands were in their control, after the registration of the property rights they also earned the possibility to sell the lands to the settled communities that desired to expand their fields as testified for example by the land sold from the ’Adawan tribe to the Madaba villagers, but also to participate in ventures with merchants to farm the lands by hiring seasonal workers and then selling the crops on the local markets, gaining higher profits than grazing stocks for self-sustainment and small trade. On the other hand Ottoman authorities gained possess of all the lands that weren’t registered and were then able to use them as grants to the tribes that accepted to use them for farming instead of pastures, therefore an overall increase in trade, productivity and productive lands was followed by an higher amount of taxes collected. Also the new land regime imposed the tribes to be included in the bureaucratic apparatus of the state if they wanted to gain from the benefits of it by registering ownership of their land, and as a consequence to accept the state’s prominent role and presence. Obviously the submission to the Empire wasn’t without consequences in tribal hierarchies, the smallest tribes faced a depriving of their main sources of income, like raiding, and the shaykhs were left without the necessary resources to maintain their standards of living nor the hospitality and redistribution traditions that granted them their higher status among the tribesmen. These losses were paid back by honours, stipends and Ottoman titles for the most important tribes, for example Bani Sakhr’s leader Sattam Fayiz was invited to Istanbul to receive the title of mudir, honours and stipends were given also to his son and to his heir after his death; another important shaikh Sattam Sha’lan was given the title of mir miran Pasa, comparable to a provincial governor, in exchange for his submission and the promise of settle down his tribe. Conversely the lack of consideration for the less important shaykhs made them turn against the imposition of the new taxes, as in the case of the Bani Hamida who stubbornly resisted the count of their herds for taxation purposes and resumed their raids against villagers, caravans and Ottoman officers until the governor of Syria led against them a military expedition in 1889. In the end &lt;em&gt;the Ottoman government recognized the limits of its authority in the steppe, and limited its demands on the tribes to higher taxation. The government did not attempt to apply measures of conscription and disarmament which were certain to provoke rebellion&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 190)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-civilizing-mission&quot;&gt;The civilizing mission&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the modernization of the Empire’s apparatus an ongoing segmentation between Ottoman (intended as “of Turkish origins”) and other subjects of the Empire took shape in state’s officers minds regarding the populations living in the “peripheries”, especially about nomadic ones. This image is part of the Ottoman modernization process that tended to build different categories interpreting those backward populations of the Empire in contrast to the modern and “westernized” Turkish elite of the core regions. This paradox in Ottoman reforms, the attempt of centralization through the inclusion of all the ethnicities of the Empire under the Ottoman citizenship, while segregating the same different cultures into the box of backwardness led to the concept of “Ottomanization” as a way out of savagery to make the tribesmen more civilized, but also as a justification for the ethnocentric and Turkish based dominating position in the Empire’s bureaucratic apparatus. Significantly the increasing integration with European markets and cultures demarcated the different relative speed of change in the various provinces of the Empire: as seen by Ottoman bureaucrats the centre lived a different timing than the peripheries thus leading to an increased span between their respective “acculturation”. Therefore the quicker integration of the centre offered a further justification to the administrators for their civilizing mission, since it deepened the already well rooted perception of barbarism in the outer provinces. During the Tanzimât era the narrowing of the distance of the Arab provinces to the centre by building infrastructures was seen as the first step of cultural inclusion. Then under the sultanat of Abdulhamid II (1876-1909) a new approach to unify the Empire under one ideology was attempted in the shape of Islamism, particularly insisting on the title of Caliph as defender of the faith and helper for Muslim populations, this was also used as a leverage when dealing with tribes pressuring on the unity of the community of the faithful. This shift to a policy more based on religion triggered counter reaction by bureaucrats and intellectuals trained in the western culture based schools founded during the Tanzimât that led to the promulgation of the first constitution. Especially the main concept of Ottomanism was expressed in the 8th article: &lt;em&gt;All subjects of the Empire are called Ottomans, without distinction whatever faith they profess; the status of an Ottoman is acquired and lost according to conditions specified by law&lt;/em&gt; . While during the Tanzimât period the main goal was to establish permanently the Empire’s presence in the frontier regions in the attempt to build a strong centralized state apparatus, in the subsequent years it become more and more important the creation of Ottoman subjects who shared a common sense of membership that let a community made of different ethnicities become a Nation. But still among Ottoman administrators prevailed a two face attitude regarding their subject: formal intolerance against diversity but pragmatic toleration especially in the case of the nomadic populations that dwelt the peripheries. In Empire’s officers view, a still pervasive interpretation of Ibn Khaldoun’s concept of “clash of civilization” persisted that drove their comments and ideas in a monolithic perception of backwardness and savagery regarding the nomadic way of life&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;Deringil2003&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;Deringil2003&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;. The need of include these population in the Empire’s labor force and army pushed the same officers to turn to the necessity of making them useful. The pragmatism that characterized the Empire’s attitude is particularly interesting in the case of Libya were, after the English conquest of Egypt and the French presence in Algeria, the foreign threat is the biggest, this was not only an enlightened policy but more a need to include the tribes in the defence of the territory since the Porte didn’t have the means to send troops in case of necessity. On this case it’s also relevant to note that in the Abdulhamid II’s memorandum prescribing the practices to follow to rule the province, the Sultan is concerned in gaining population’s hearts, so to make it possible to form a local armed force in case of need to resist a foreign invasion without the need to send troops. This is supposed to be achieved by boosting local economy with direct investments from the Empire’s treasure and importing modern equipment and tools from Europe to improve the effectiveness of agricultural practices, but also to renovate the city showing the population the positive side effects of “civilization”. In the regions along the coast of the Red Sea, namely Hicaz and Yemen, the increase of geopolitical importance not only by the ran for colonialism in Africa but also for the inauguration of the Suez’ channel (1869), the most relevant feeling in the local governors is a sense of urgency in imposing the presence of the state by building infrastructures and stressing on the need to educate the Arabs then to include local sheykhs in administration of the province, all traits that outline the civilizing mission was pursued by Ottoman officers appointed to rule the provinces. The building of schools in the villages to be attended by tribesmen’s sons was partly a reaction to the increasing influence of missionaries who were indoctrinating the young in their schools, but also a mean to infuse Ottoman principles and ideas to the future generations, turning them into citizens and to teach them the use of Turkish as a common language, so during &lt;em&gt;the Hamidian era mass education was extended to the primary school level&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;deringil1998well&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;deringil1998well&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 94)&lt;/span&gt; Especially the turn to Islam as a common trait on which build the new sense of unity among the subjects of the Empire was going to be extremely influential in the definition of the curricula of the secondary schools. The increasing amount of hours in class for religious training and the enforcement on religious practice was particularly deep in the military schools were the students missing one prayer were prohibited to leave the school on the days off and in case of missing the ramadan feasting they were convicted in school’s prison&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;deringil1998well&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;deringil1998well&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 97)&lt;/span&gt; The infusion of a “sacred sense of duty” was predominant in the School of Civil Administration and the attempt to create a new administrative state elite faithful both to the doctrine of Islam and to the sultan was one of Abdulhamid II’s main concerns. Also the institution of a group of Sunni Muslim missionaries to contrast the widespread heresy present in the Empire’s territories, like shi’a, and the influence of Christian missionaries too often sponsored by European countries to pursue their interests, like France and the Russian Empire and their protection respectively on the catholic and orthodox communities in the Empire. The control on the non-Muslim schools sharpened during Abdulhamid II’s sultanat first with the new Education Law that allowed educational commissions to control the syllabi then with the increased number of orders to close down schools that weren’t conformed with the Ministry of Education’s regulations. Governors in peripheral provinces also stressed the necessity to improve the teaching of Turkish starting from primary school to create a sense of membership to the same community between the different ethnicities. &lt;em&gt;Clearly, the ibtidayie and rüşdiye schools that the imperial centre was encouraged to institute in the region were envisioned as so many fortresses against foreign penetration.[..]hand in hand with the mission civilizatrice, as the vali did not neglect to state that the tribes ’who live in a state of nomadism, savagery and ignorance’, had to be ’brought into the community of the civilized people’&lt;/em&gt; [pg 100[&lt;span&gt;deringil1998well&lt;/span&gt; The necessity to use education to create a suitable environment to rule the peripheral regions was both a suggestion from local officers who recognized the usefulness to infuse the populations with Ottoman ideals and an active policy of the Sultan to build a new community faithful to him. With this kind of premises the foundation of the Aşiret Mektebi seems a logical consequence. Two steps led to the realization of the tribe school: first 48 students from peripheral provinces were invited to Istanbul to study at the military academy, after they graduated were appointed to honored positions in their home regions for &lt;em&gt;both in town and among your own [tribes] many children who see you will wish to be like you&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan1996acsiret&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;rogan1996acsiret&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 85)&lt;/span&gt;. Then Ottoman authorities succeeded in inviting Sattam al-Sha’lan, the shaykh of one of the most important arab tribes in Syrian province, to come in Istanbul and after he committed to settle his people the Porte granted him honors, and promoted him to pasha, the shaykh even left one of his sons in the city to be given an Ottoman education. This event had a great impression on other shaykhs of the same region and many of them followed his lead, thus proving the success of this policy as we can see in Ottoman archives the numerous petition asking for official invitation to the capitol in the hope to receive the same grants. Actually the state’s project (and hope) was more related to shaykhs’ sons, since the arab rulers were too old to be indoctrinated their young sons were a perfect bet for a long term policy of inclusion: the institution of a school for the future leaders of nomadic tribes influencing their cultural formation and infusing them with the concepts of Ottoman citizenship and loyalty to the Sultan. In this way both the “civilizing mission” and the conquest of the heart and mind of Arab tribes could be accomplished. Despite this “glorious” premise, the tribe school never reached really the hearts of all the tribes: instead the estimated total of 450 alumni just 88 were enrolled in the first three years. Also an example of a graduate behavior after he got back to his tribe can witness how the program was only partially successful: Muhammad Barjis al-Farham, from Aleppo province, was met by a Czech geographer that reported him saying that the school made him familiar to Ottoman bureaucracy and customs, but this knowledge let him &lt;em&gt;coax large tracts of land from the Government, both for himself and his tribe&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan1996acsiret&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;rogan1996acsiret&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 97)&lt;/span&gt; more than feeling loyalty and gratefulness to the Ottomans. At least his project was to settle down his people and turn his land in productive fields thus partially fulfilling the goals of Ottoman’s administration. On the other side many graduates served the Empire up to its end. An overall evaluation of this social engineering project is impossible to achieve since this kind of experiments need time to develop and to reach their goal: the school was founded in 1892 and closed in 1907 cause of a student rebellion, and the Empire was on the edge of its dissolution culminated in 1923.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;hybrid-sovereignty-and-the-nationalist-discourse&quot;&gt;Hybrid sovereignty and the Nationalist discourse&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three trajectories are recognized in the Empire contrasting the well-established interpretation of center versus periphery &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;Emrence2008&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;Emrence2008&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 298)&lt;/span&gt;: coastal, characterized by the inclusion in the European sphere of influence through the port cities and trade networks, and represented by the Western Anatolia, Lebanon and the Mediterranean provinces of Rumelia, interior who was the core area of the Empire: Anatolia, Syria and Palestine, mostly populated by Arab and Turkish farmers and herders, and the frontier were the authority of the Sultan was extremely tenuous, in some cases even inconsistent&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 42)&lt;/span&gt;. The discourse of the injection of Ottoman ideals in the Transjordan region is a process of intrusion after the opening of the frontier&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;rogan2002frontiers&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 5)&lt;/span&gt;, the Ottomanization discourse penetrated the territories by creating new settlements and induced an optimization of the land use in the area, increased the tax extraction and included the local notables in a more centralized administration. The need to constantly rely on bargaining practices to relate with the tribes or even to leave them dealing with internal struggles, like what happened for the registration of land when every tribe decided how and on which name(s) register the ownership, didn’t eradicate the local networks of kin and trade relations that were precedent the intrusion of the Empire. As a consequence the prominent role that officers, governors and the Sultan himself had to grant to the most important shaykhs allowed the enhancement of their relative power and the enlargement of their networks, especially those who were successful in extending their influence as trade partners of the merchants who were attracted by the establishment of new commercial networks thanks to the enhanced security ensured by the Empire’s presence. Thus the intrusion of the Ottomans and their co-opting practices broke &lt;em&gt;the circular, self perpetuating, and self reinforcing mechanism inherent [..] self administering groups [that] result in a weak or absent central agency&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;gellner1991tribes&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;gellner1991tribes&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 109)&lt;/span&gt; with the side effect of an increase of the relative power of the shaykhs’ authority among their own tribes. As &lt;em&gt;a large, functioning empire goes through a continuous cycle of building up power in its peripheral units only to see those who have direct access to that power turn it to their own ends&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;tilly1975formation&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;tilly1975formation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 29)&lt;/span&gt;, what was taking shape in Transjordan along with the increasing presence and efficiency of the Ottoman bureaucratic apparatus was a hybrid sovereignty&lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;bacik2007hybrid&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;bacik2007hybrid&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; characterized by the overlapping presence of more than one hegemonic discourse. The peculiarity of the context was that after a first Ottoman intrusion mostly characterized by violence to impose direct rule and the reforms of the Tanzimât, the policies to maintain the control of the region shifted to a more inclusive attitude deeply relying on the role of established pattern of power based on the local elites, especially during the Hamidian period with the attempts to conquer the hearts of the population and the social engineering experiment of the Tribe School. There isn’t a neat distinction in these two approaches since the military campaigns to penetrate the southernmost parts of Transjordan continued up the the end of the 19th century (thus under Abdulhamid II sultanat) and it seems more an adaptive strategy of the rule strategies that actually begun just with the first attempts to impose the reforms, as the appointed governors were using a firm hand as a last resort relying more on participating actively in the improvement of the cities and villages by building infrastructures and collective buildings. As we have seen for example in the application of the Land Reform or in the Abdulhamid II’s memorandum a common trait of the Ottoman officers was a pragmatic approach to deal with the tribes, more based on achieving the final result by bargaining or bribing with gifts and titles that on the straight imposition of Sultan’s rule by strength, the same strategy used for example to enter Karak durign the first expansion in Transjordan. The change in the attitude if Ottoman officers toward the so called civilizing mission was a consequence of the need to progressively include the tribes and “uncivilized” populations into the increasing centralized administrative practices of the Empire, that paradoxically led to the creation a conceptual distinction between the Ottoman elite and its subjects in what Selim Deringil calls a moral distance between the two, and that he acknowledges as being a main similarity to a colonialist behavior in the Empire’s elite. At the beginning of the 19th century, after the young Turks came into power, this process &lt;em&gt;heated up, some of the Arabists accused the CUP of having been intent on concentrating the power of the state in Turkish hands and treating the non-Turkish elements in the Ottoman Empire just like colonial France treated the Algerians&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;Deringil2003&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;Deringil2003&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; pg 341)&lt;/span&gt; Despite the comparison with the Hapsburg and Russian Empires on the basis that none of them successfully faced the challenge of modern Nation states &lt;span class=&quot;citation&quot; data-cites=&quot;barkey2008empire&quot;&gt;(&lt;span class=&quot;citeproc-not-found&quot; data-reference-id=&quot;barkey2008empire&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; it is interesting to notice that Ottoman Empire shows some similarities also with the Italian and (to some extent) German cases, all of them faced the unification and centralization process in the “second wave” of state and nation building during the 19th century and all of them first had to impose the center’s prominent role in their “peripheries” (with the due differences of course) and then strengthening the role of education to grasp people’s hearts and to build the collective consciousness at the basis of the nation-building. Then after the 1st World War they turned in strong nationalistic and ethnocentric autocratic (dictatorial) regimes. In this sense the Tanzimât reforms can be interpreted not as a failed attempt to achieve modernity in the struggle to survive posed by the challenging European Nation states but part of a long term process that eventually contributed to put the basis for the birth of the Turkish republic after the loss of the outer provinces of the Ottoman Empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;bibliography&quot; class=&quot;unnumbered&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;refs&quot; class=&quot;references&quot;&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-rogan_frontiers_1999&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rogan, E L. 1999. &lt;em&gt;Frontiers of the State in the Late Ottoman Empire: Transjordan, 1850-1921&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 12. Cambridge University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;ref-scott_art_2009&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott, J C. 2009. &lt;em&gt;The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Upland Southeast Asia&lt;/em&gt;. Yale University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2015/12/ottomans</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2015/12/ottomans</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Notes on Neoliberism</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;theoretical-approach-as-a-consequence-of-amartya-sens-paradox-as-we-can-see-in-the-definitionanalysis-of-neoliberism-proposed-by-wacquant-and-in-the-proposed-applications-of-neoliberist-methods-and-techniques-to-social-welfare-purposes-by-ferguson&quot;&gt;theoretical approach as a consequence of amartya sen’s paradox as we can see in the definition/analysis of neoliberism proposed by wacquant and in the proposed applications of neoliberist methods and techniques to social welfare purposes by ferguson:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The liberal paradox is a logical paradox advanced by Amartya Sen, building on the work of Kenneth Arrow and his impossibility theorem, which showed that within a system of menu-independent social choice, it is impossible to have both a commitment to “Minimal Liberty”, which was defined as the ability to order tuples of choices, and Pareto optimality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most contentious aspect is, on one hand, to contradict the libertarian notion that the market mechanism is sufficient to produce a Pareto-optimal society—and on the other hand, argue that degrees of choice and freedom, rather than welfare economics, should be the defining trait of that market mechanism. As a result it attracts commentary from both the left and the right of the political spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ABOUT PARETO’S EFFICIENCY: In a Pareto efficient economic allocation, no one can be made better off without making at least one individual worse off. Given an initial allocation of goods among a set of individuals, a change to a different allocation that makes at least one individual better off without making any other individual worse off is called a Pareto improvement. An allocation is defined as “Pareto efficient” or “Pareto optimal” when no further Pareto improvements can be made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pareto efficiency is a minimal notion of efficiency and does not necessarily result in a socially desirable distribution of resources: it makes no statement about equality, or the overall well-being of a society. The notion of Pareto efficiency can also be applied to the selection of alternatives in engineering and similar fields. Each option is first assessed under multiple criteria and then a subset of options is identified with the property that no other option can categorically outperform any of its members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;wacquant&quot;&gt;WACQUANT&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;startin point: ethnogpraphy in the chicago ghettos that conducted the author to analyze the increasing oppressive policies in what he calls “the america’s gargantuan carceral system”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so the purpose of the paper is to link the micro (????) ethnography of the “postindustrial precariat” to the macro sociology of the neoliberal leviathan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;from here he analyzes the realization of neoliberist programs and their reflection in society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;identifies three common traits in the application of these policies as summarized in the end of the paper&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;from a theoretical point of view he sees the: neoliberalism as an articulation of state, market and citizenship that harnesses the first to impose the stamp of the second onto the third&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;also useful in defining is the concept of: governmentality (foucault) but devoid of specifity in its definition ofgoverning through calculation, so it can be applied almost everywhere but doesn’t really add further undertsnding in trying to define neoliberalsm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as an example he draws from the conclusions of his ethnographic research that starting from the 70ies there is an active tendency of the us government to racialise poverty and to apply increasingly repressive measures to deal with the reactions against the consequences of market deregulation and withdrawal of social welfare system&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;confirmation of this theory is seen in the battle against street crime pusrued almost by every left government in europe after 1990 in author’s words:in sum, the penalisation of poverty emerged as a core element of the domestic implementation and transborder diffusion of the neoliberal project, the ‘iron fist’ of the penal state mating with the ‘invisible hand’ of the market in conjunction with the fraying of the social safety net&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2 main views about understanding neoliberism : 1) self regulationg market – state’s withdrawal as a role just to allow building a framework into which an autonomous development of economic practices based on free market can be realized&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2)governmentality- active presence of the state in realizing through practices whose purpose is to shape people (subjects-citizens) and societal relations a new “commodization of everything”- based economy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;since the second agrues mainly about practices through realizing neoliberism also recognizes that it’s not a monolithic concept but actually is extremely dependent on the context : there is not one big-n neoliberalism but an indefinite number of small-n neoliberalisms born of the ongoing hybridisation of neoliberal practices and ideas with local conditions and forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;since everything can be recognized as a local variation in an increasing particularism that can’t allow any kind of general abstraction into theory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;=&amp;gt;requires a generalized normativity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the author poses himself in a via media [proposed is] in the sense that it defiles from pure governmentality or market center conceptions from the fact that recognize a preminence in state actions to achieve economic ends in redrawing its inner societal boundaries and relations accordingly to market conforming policies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;=&amp;gt;from a ‘thin’ economic conception centred on the market to a ‘thick’ sociological conception centred on the state that specifies the institutional machinery involved in the establishment of market dominance and its operant impact on effective social membership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;main goal : is to find common practices in the attempt to obtain a neater definition of neoliberalism, three main thesis are discussed: (1) neoliberalism is not an economic regime but a political project of state-crafting that puts disciplinary ‘workfare’, neutralising ‘prisonfare’ and the trope of individual responsibility at the service of commodification;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;market is part of the political arena: mauss, polanyi ecc. demonstrated social and economic relations are strictly intertwined, as a consequence there are social reactions to attempts of commodization and the state must overcome this opposition. thus neoliberism poses itself in the middle between socialist and keynesian collective solutions and the pure liberist self-regulationg market&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 main points to realize that: commodization, disciplinary social policy (social assistance is made conditional upon submission to flexible employment), expansive and pornographic (????????) penalty , the use of individual responsibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot; type=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;neoliberalism entails a rightward tilting of the space of bureaucratic agencies that define and distribute public goods and spawns a centaur-state that practises liberalism at the top of the class structure and punitive paternalism at the bottom; using bourdieu terms, the boureaucratic space is where the state makes the shift to the marketization/commodization of its own systems- punishing the poor by moving resources to the social to the penal wing and by including neoliberist techniques in the management of welfare, health care education ecc. (shift from left hand feminine policies to right hand and masculine– coercitive)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the growth and glorification of the penal wing of the state is an integral component of the neoliberal leviathan, such that the police, courts and prison need to be brought into the political anthropology of neoliberal rule.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as a consequence of point 2 an increasing repressive policy and overall amount of inmates has surged along the establishment of market economy, especially against the “weak” segments of society that were the most affected by the changes in welfare system and labor market pusrued by the state. examples: - aggressive deployment of the police - increased recourse to the courts to handle unruly behavior and minor offenses mushrooming of administrative retention centres to corral and expel irregular migrants boom of a media sector trading on catastrophic images of criminal danger&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;upon examining trends in a dozen advanced societies distributed among four types of political economy, cavadino and dignan report ‘a general tendency for changes in these countries’ punishment levels over time [fitting] the same pattern: ‘as a society moves in the direction of neo-liberalism, its punishment becomes harsher’ examples: us after 1970 chile and latin america in the early 80ies    and england during 90&amp;#39;s
1)control and suppress potential insurgents and destabylizing factors
2)reestablish trhough coercion the legitimacy of political  leadership against the increasing role played by the market&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as a conclusion we can see how this resemble more as an ongoing process of state formation/building than a pure shift in political-economy and thus should be analysed accordingly to this view, the different elements and outcomes as part of a process that has also to adapt to local peculiarities. in the author’s interpretation so we can outline that the three points extrapolated can be a common trait in the transformations that are involved in this process&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;historical anthropology of neoliberalism as it actually evolves we must acknowledge that it pertains to the register of state formation. much like the ‘long sixteenth century’ saw the birth of the modern leviathan in western europe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;james-ferguson&quot;&gt;james ferguson&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for over the last couple of decades, what we call “the left” has come to be organized, in large part, around a project of resisting and refusing harmful new developments in the world. leftist policies defined as anti instead of pro as if the only space left is the opposition to neoliberist policies; studies of state and development tend, with depressing predictability, to conclude (in tones of righteous indignation) that the rich are benefiting and the poor are getting screwed. any realistic sort of progressive politics that would seek a serious answer to the question “what do we want?” will have to involve an exploration of the contemporary possibilities for developing genuinely progressive arts of government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;lack of an ensemble of ideas to characterize an active leftist policy :1979 foucault lecture: “absence of a socialist artof government” the challenge is how to implement socialist ideas in a market economy since there’s no possibility to “go back” and recreate the socio-political setting that was in exestence before ’70ies, left politicians and ideologists have to find a way to include poverty question and social welfare into the contemporary context of neoliberism and free market&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1)shift from the keynesian welfare system as a pact between “workers” and individuals that required social intervention (elderly, infirm ecc) due to the increasing amount of unemployed and informal workers that are in the same needs even if they should be part of the labor force&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2)increasing separation between state and social policy delegating the latter to ngo’s and international organizations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;can we imagine new “arts of government” that might take advantage of (rather than simply denouncing or resisting) recent transformations in the spatial organization of government and social assistance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we need to develop new ways of thinking that don’t take for granted previously fundamental categories like “the worker” or “the nation-state” since their no more effective&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;=&amp;gt;in which ways we can use neoliberism to apply progressive policies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;there is a clear analysis in this literature of what it is that distinguishes “neoliberalism” from liberalism. liberalism, in this account, was always about finding the right balance between two spheres understood as properly distinct, if always related: state and market, public and private, the realm of the king and the proper domain of the merchant. neoliberalism, in contrast, puts governmental mechanisms developed in the private sphere to work within the state itself, so that even core functions of the state are either subcontracted out to private providers, or run “like a business”. the question of what should be public and what private becomes blurred, as the state itself increasingly organizes itself around “profit centers”, “enterprise models”, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;neoliberism as a confusing term:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we may consider the new governmental rationalities that emerged through the thatcher–reagan assaults on the north atlantic, post-war welfare state. key here was the deployment of market mechanisms and “enterprise” models to reform government, construction of active and rational citizens able to act in the new shape of the society&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;thus said if we look at the application of neoliberism in africa, we can see that it has really few of neo: its mostly similar just to liberist deregulation of market to allow the intrusion of foreign capitals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;from a certain point of view the author seems to define the term neoliberism as a neutral and descriptive concept more related to methodologies of “governmentality” than to a politic vies strictly speaking, thus he argues that these same methods can be diverted and used for social purposes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;one possible way to exploit market economy for progressist purposes is the south african basic income grant the argument goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;markets aren’t working for poor people because they’re too poor to participate in them;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;government programs aren’t working because the state is inefficient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so, provide income support directly, in the form of cash, and then say to the poor: “you are now empowered to solve your own problems in the way you see best”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the reasoning here often includes recognizably neoliberal elements, including the valorization of market efficiency, individual choice, and autonomy; themes of entrepreneurship; and skepticism about the state as a service provider but the purpose is a pro poor policy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the idea of a big was first put forward by the labor union federation, cosatu, in 1998, and it acquired new legitimacy when it was embraced in 2002 by a government-appointed committee (the taylor committee) charged with recommending measures for the rationalization of the system of social assistance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the big campaign is significant not only as an interesting and potentially progressive policy proposal, but also as an illustration of some new ways of thinking about questions of poverty and welfare that bring neoliberal themes to bear on the question of social assistance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a big, supporters say, would enable poor south africans to increase their spending on such things as nutrition, education, and health care. and this, advocates insist, should be understood as an “investment” in a kind of “capital”. such “investment”, they insist, will bring handsome returns, in the form of productivity gains. the poor individual is in this way conceived, in classic neoliberal fashion, as a kind of micro-enterprise, earning a rate of return on invested capital. combating dependency the existing “safety net”, the big promoters argue, relies on very destructive forms of dependency since any economically productive poor person is surrounded by relatives and other dependents who must be supported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;providing basic income security for all, it is claimed, will enable the poor to behave as proper neoliberal subjects (ie as entrepreneurs and risk takers); the status quo prevents it, and promotes “dependency”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;they would not need the government to tell them how to spend the funds. they would use them (like good rational actors) in the way they saw best. there would be no “nanny state”: no policing of conduct, no stigmatizing labels, no social workers coming into homes and no costly bureaucracy to sort out who does or doesn’t qualify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;social payments, in this optic, are most significant not as temporary substitutes for employment, but as a way of promoting greater productivity, enterprise, and risk-taking in the “informal” domain within which more and more south africans are expected to make their living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;food aid and cash transfers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the example i have in mind is the increasingly influential argument that hunger is best dealt with by boosting the purchasing power of those at risk, rather than by distributing in-kind food aid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;actual system of food aid relies mainly on surplus production in rich countries and its redistribution to people in risk of hunger&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;negative impacts of such policies, which tend to depress producer prices for local farmers,while damaging local institutions for producing and distributing food crops. once food aid has arrived, local food production may never recover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as an alternative,amartya sen’s followers have pushed for cash payments to be made directly to those at risk of food deficit: people with money in their pockets, these advocates point out, usually don’t starve dispensing cash, they insist, is in the first place more efficient and less expensive than other sorts of assistance,and often requires less infrastructure and institutional capacity. in any case, they argue, why should bureaucrats decide on behalf of recipients what their needs are? and poor people, in this conception, are good judges of how to do that—using money to go to the clinic this month, to pay school fees for a child the next, to buy a bag of maize meal the next, and so on. rather than wasting the money on frivolous expenditure, advocates insist, recipients generally apply their scant cash resources very rationally, and even make canny small investments. top-down, state-planned attempts to directly meet nutritional needs through trucking in food, in this view, are bound to be clumsy, inefficient, and wasteful&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;consider, guyer suggests, how food ends up finding its way to consumers’ plates in the vast megacities of west africa such as lagos. the logistical task of moving thousands of tons of food each day from thousands of local producers to millions of urban consumers would be beyond the organizational capacity of any state such forms of organization must appear especially attractive where states lack capacity (and let us remember how many progressive dreams in africa have crashed on the rocks of low state capacity).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;market-based solutions are thus likely to be true “solutions” only for the better- off, whose needs are so effectively catered to by markets. but the food aid example shows a way of redirecting markets toward the poor, by intervening not to restrict the market, but to boost purchasing power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;steven collier (2005) has recently pointed out, it is important to question the assumption that there is, or must be, a neat or automatic fit between a hegemonic “neoliberal” political-economic project (however that might be characterized), on the one hand, and specific “neoliberal” techniques, on the other social technologies need not have any essential or eternal loyalty to the political formations within which they were first developed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the answers to the left’s governmental problems require not yet another search through our sacred texts, but a process of conceptual and institutional innovation. “[i]f there is a really socialist governmentality, then it is not hidden within socialism and its texts. it cannot be deduced from them. it must be invented”. but invention in the domain of governmental technique is rarely something worked up out of whole cloth. more often, it involves a kind of bricolage begin making an inventory of the parts available and what kind of purpose they may serve go beyond seeing neoliberism as evil learn to use governmental technique for new social purposes&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2015/10/neoliberism_notes</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://rizzoli.me.uk/notebook/2015/10/neoliberism_notes</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
